{"tossups": [{"question": "One of these events is believed to have contributed to a shift in European fauna known as the \u201cGrande Coupure\u201d. Evidence for one of these events was discovered in 2014 in the Barberton Greenstone Belt. The existence of one of these events somewhere in Southeast Asia approximately 790,000 years ago is supported by the wide spread of lechatelierite-bearing rocks throughout Australasia. Two of these events, one in the Chesapeake Bay and the other in (*) Popigai, Siberia, occurred near the boundary between the Eocene and Oligocene. A spike in the level of iridium in sediments across the world resulted from one of these events most famously investigated by Luis and Walter Alvarez. For 10 points, identify these events, the most famous of which was the cause of the extinction of the non-avian dinosaurs.", "answer": "meteor impacts (accept answers suggesting that a large, extraterrestrial object is hitting the Earth)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>meteor impacts</u></b>", "acceptable": ["meteor impacts"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept answers suggesting that a large, extraterrestrial object is hitting the Earth"}, {"question": "In 1939, a proposal to lower the speed limit of this province to 50 mph for safety reasons was made by Toby Sexsmith, who also claimed that only the premier had the need to travel faster. The surveying of geologist Robert Bell allowed for the construction of the railroads that connected this province\u2019s capital to cities in the east and to its primary port. Due to an inability to acquire nails, rawhide cords called shaganappi were used in a colony in this province to fashion its namesake carts, used for transporting fur and bison products. (*) The Dawson Road was the first means of accessing this province by land and entirely within Canada and was used by the Wolseley Expedition to put down a rebellion in this province. Difficulty in communication and transportation with eastern Canada contributed to, for 10 points, which province\u2019s Red River Rebellion?\u00a0", "answer": "Manitoba", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Manitoba</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Manitoba"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Two answers required The only known mention of a man named Hagnothemis is as an informant in a conspiracy theory in which one of these people was involved in the poisoning of the other. A scholar in the employ of one of these men, who was also the great-nephew of the other, was killed for conspiring to kill that employer with the page Hermolaus. The death of one of these men led the other to flee to Chalcis after being accused of impiety by Eurymedon the Hierophant. The relationship between these two men began on the condition that the city of (*) Stagira be rebuilt. The Secretum Secretorum is a purported letter sent from one of these men to the other on a variety of academic subjects, which was popular in medieval Europe. These two mostly interacted at Mieza where the older of these two men also taught the future Diadochi Cassander and Ptolemy I. For 10 points, identify this teacher-student pair, one the author of the Nicomachean Ethics and the other the son of Philip II of Macedon.", "answer": "Aristotle of Stagira and Alexander the Great (both parts required in either order; accept Aristot\u00e9l\u0113s or Alexander III of Macedon)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Aristotle of Stagira and Alexander the Great</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Aristotle of Stagira and Alexander the Great"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "both parts required in either order; accept Aristot\u00e9l\u0113s or Alexander III of Macedon"}, {"question": "A story of the Yuin people of this country tells of how nearby killer whales would drive other whales to the shore, where the Yuin would kill the animal and share it with the killer whales and neighboring tribes. In the southeast of this country, people gathered in huge numbers to collect estivating bogong moths, which were roasted and sometimes ground and made into smoked cakes. Peoples in the Strzelecki (cheh-\u201cLET-ski\u201d) Desert in this country made bread from ground nardoo seeds. Extensive eel traps were made in and around Lake Condah in this country, potentially supporting 10,000 people, by the (*) Gunditjmara [goon-deetch-mah-rah] people. Woodlands, hunting grounds, and farmlands were created and regulated in this country through the use of fire-stick farming. For 10 points, identify this country whose land was carefully managed by its aboriginal peoples to maximize food production in places like the Outback.", "answer": "Australia", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Australia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Australia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A poorly substantiated account claims that the commander of an expedition to this place was killed by his own soldier, Benjamin Bolling, because of the commander\u2019s disregard for his troops\u2019 lives in battle. James Grant made a disastrous attempt to take this place after severely underestimating the size of its garrison. Daniel Li\u00e9nard de Beaujeu outfitted himself as a Native American warrior to rally his troops in a battle fought to defend this place. This place was part of a series of fortifications including Fort Machault and Fort Le Boeuf. The sash of a commander killed on his way to this place is now held at (*) Mount Vernon. The Forbes Expedition drove the French garrison from this place, which had earlier been the target of a failed campaign by Edward Braddock. For 10 points, identify this 18th century French fort on the site of modern Pittsburgh.", "answer": "Fort Duquesne", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Fort Duquesne</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Fort Duquesne"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man was on a mission to Belgium when his wife Antoinette Charpentier died in childbirth. This man\u2019s lack of writing ability led him to partner with a man who published the newspaper Histoire des R\u00e9volutions de France et de Brabant and popularized the revolutionary cockade. He faced allegations of profiteering over the dissolution of the French East India company after the arrest of Fabre d\u2019Eglantine. A faction led by this man was opposed by Jacques (*) H\u00e9bert, and he allegedly wept and said, \u201cI shall not be able to save them\u201d after failing to prevent the execution of the Girondins. This man frequently collaborated with the journalist Camille Desmoulins, and he was the founder of the Cordeliers club. This man was Minister of Justice of a provisional government during the September Massacres, and he was guillotined in April 1794 along with other members of his Indulgents faction. For 10 points, name this first president of the Committee of Public Safety and opponent of the Reign of Terror.\u00a0", "answer": "Georges Jacques Danton", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Georges Jacques Danton</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Georges Jacques Danton"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Geographer Matthew Edney has challenged the interpretation that a mural at this site, potentially depicting an erupting Mt. Hasan, is a map of the local area. Burials at this site have been primarily found in what have been dubbed \u201chistory houses\u201d, which, despite their symbolic importance, display no special economic or political importance. The presence of bulls in ceremonial contexts and the greater frequency of explicitly male animals in iconography was used in a 2011 paper to argue for a \u201cphallocentrism\u201d at this site, which contrasts the Mother Goddess cult position advanced by (*) James Mellaart. Excavation at this site was revived in 1993 in part to further the post-processual archaeology of Ian Hodder. Iconography of a large, seated woman flanked by lions at this site may show worship of a precursor to the goddess Cybele of later Anatolian religion. For 10 points, identify this Neolithic site in southern Turkey.", "answer": "\u00c7atalh\u00f6y\u00fck (chah-TAHL-hey-yook) (accept \u00c7atalh\u00fcy\u00fck)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\u00c7atalh\u00f6y\u00fck</u></b>", "acceptable": ["\u00c7atalh\u00f6y\u00fck"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "chah-TAHL-hey-yook"}, {"question": "According to one story, a state of this ethnic group converted to Islam after a merchant healed a desperately ill king and his wife; that state would build The Black Chamber and the Cathedral Mosque. The fall of an empire ruled by this ethnic group, ruled in its pagan period by the Dulo, Vokil and Ugain clans, was delayed by four brothers of the Cometopuli dynasty. A branch of this ethnic group settled in Byzantine territory after allying with the Seven Tribes of (*) Slavs at the Battle of Ongal, while a Muslim group of this ethnicity settled around the Volga River. A second empire of this ethnicity, which had adopted a Slavic language related to Old Church Slavonic, was led from a capital claimed to be a \u201cNew Constantinople\u201d, Tarnovo, by Kaloyan and Ivan Asen. For 10 points, identify this ethnic group that frequently clashed with the Byzantine Empire over control of the Balkans, who Basil II is known for slaying.", "answer": "Bulgarians (accept Volga Bulgars)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Bulgarians</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Bulgarians"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Volga Bulgars"}, {"question": "Herodotus accurately recorded that these people spread soil onto salt when planting crops to bring out water. These people built the mountain-top city of Zinchecra which sits north of their namesake city between hundreds of small pyramidal tombs where people were buried vertically. A series of defensive limes [lee-mace] north of these peoples\u2019 lands, were intended to protect cities like Sabratha and (*) Oea. Misconceptions about these people\u2019s civilization partially come from Herodotus' account that they were warlike-people who hunted the cave-dwelling troglodytes. This civilization, which extracted fossil water out of extensive foggara tunnel systems, likely collapsed after these supplies ran out. During the Roman Empire, these people benefited from their place at the center of a trans-Sahara \u201cchariot-route\u201d trade network of gold, slaves, and ivory. For 10 points, name this ancient urban civilization centered in southern Libya.\u00a0", "answer": "Garamentes", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Garamentes</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Garamentes"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Some historians believe that this region\u2019s town of Wolin, called Jumne by Adam of Bremen was the base of a group founded by Palnatoke, which was destroyed by Magnus the Good according to the Heimskringla; other historians place that base in land now under the sea in this region\u2019s island of Usedom. A gold disc artifact found in this region inscribed with Danish king Harold Bluetooth\u2019s name supports the theory that a semi-legendary group of Norse holy warriors called the (*) Jomsvikings [yohms-vee-keengs] were based in its town of Jomsborg [yohms-bohrg]. A ruler born in this region to the House of Griffin was deposed after the Engelbrekt rebellion. That ruler from this region introduced a tax on trade through his territory called the Sound Dues and changed his name from Bogus\u0142aw (baw-goo-\u201dsuave\u201d) after succeeding Margaret I. For 10 points, name this region on the Baltic Sea that was the birthplace of Eric, king of the Kalmar Union.", "answer": "Pomerania\u00a0  11. Exact wording required Academic skepticism on the authenticity of the most common version of this quote has cited the lack of fear tactics and profanity used in the speech containing it. Upon hearing its most famous utterance, Edward Carrington supposedly chose to be buried where he heard this quote said. This quote may have been inspired by the final line of Act II, Scene IV of Cato, a Tragedy, a popular play at the time. The oldest reconstruction of the speech containing this quote comes from the glowing biography of its deliverer written by (*) William Wirt. This quote ended a speech given to rally the delegates of the Second Virginia Convention into creating a militia. For 10 points, give this sentence, supposedly uttered by Patrick Henry, that displayed his fervor for emancipation from British rule. ANSWER: \u201cGive me liberty, or give me death!\u201d", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Pomerania\u00a0  11. Exact wording required Academic skepticism on the authenticity of the most common version of this quote has cited the lack of fear tactics and profanity used in the speech containing it. Upon hearing its most famous utterance, Edward Carrington supposedly chose to be buried where he heard this quote said. This quote may have been inspired by the final line of Act II, Scene IV of Cato, a Tragedy, a popular play at the time. The oldest reconstruction of the speech containing this quote comes from the glowing biography of its deliverer written by</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Pomerania\u00a0  11. Exact wording required Academic skepticism on the authenticity of the most common version of this quote has cited the lack of fear tactics and profanity used in the speech containing it. Upon hearing its most famous utterance, Edward Carrington supposedly chose to be buried where he heard this quote said. This quote may have been inspired by the final line of Act II, Scene IV of Cato, a Tragedy, a popular play at the time. The oldest reconstruction of the speech containing this quote comes from the glowing biography of its deliverer written by"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "*"}, {"question": "Exact wording required Academic skepticism on the authenticity of the most common version of this quote has cited the lack of fear tactics and profanity used in the speech containing it. Upon hearing its most famous utterance, Edward Carrington supposedly chose to be buried where he heard this quote said. This quote may have been inspired by the final line of Act II, Scene IV of Cato, a Tragedy, a popular play at the time. The oldest reconstruction of the speech containing this quote comes from the glowing biography of its deliverer written by (*) William Wirt. This quote ended a speech given to rally the delegates of the Second Virginia Convention into creating a militia. For 10 points, give this sentence, supposedly uttered by Patrick Henry, that displayed his fervor for emancipation from British rule.", "answer": "Tajiks", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tajiks</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tajiks"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "According to a scholar of these people, Xiren [xee-ren] Kurban, their name comes from an ancient word for \u201csole crown\u201d their ancient kings wore, or the bright coloured hats worn in imitation. The Kart dynasty was a family of princes of this ethnicity that briefly ruled autonomously after decades under Mongol rule. In a country where these people are a minority, Sharof Rashidov demanded that they identify as the majority ethnic group or emigrate. Universities teaching in these people\u2019s language, located in a country where they are a minority, have been closed by the (*) Islam Karimov regime as part of a larger campaign of repression. These people\u2019s distinct cultural identity from their Turkic neighbours is usually traced to Persian immigration during the Samanid Empire. For 10 points, identify this Persian-speaking ethnic group, who spent centuries ruled by Uzbeks and Russians until the fall of the Soviet Union left them with a mountainous country ruled by Emomali Rahmon from Dushanbe.", "answer": "The Last Kingdom", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Last Kingdom</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Last Kingdom"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a June 2020 tweet, Ricky Gervais expressed his love for this series with a picture of himself bare-chested and wearing braids and face paint. A man in this series repeatedly shouts \u201cBetter than barley!\u201d while having sex with a girl in his lord\u2019s bed, and is later killed by that lord for stealing timber. Another man in this series kills his lord by tightening the bandages around his head, an action that forces him into self-exile because it was seen by his sister Eadith. A character in this series is able to convince a lord to uphold a pardon after being inspired by a vision of his dead friend (*) Leofric (LAY-oh-fritch). The son of the protagonist of this series is saved by Father Beocca during a failed attempt to retake Bebbanburg. Uhtred Ragnarsson is the protagonist of, for 10 points, what Netflix television series based on The Saxon Stories books by Bernard Cornwell?", "answer": "jadeite\u00a0", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>jadeite</u></b>", "acceptable": ["jadeite"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Maya believed that this material could breathe and, when placed in the mouth, could capture the \u201cbreath soul\u201d of the recently deceased. The Sacred Cenote of Chich\u00e9n Itz\u00e1 contains the largest collection of Mayan objects of this material, which may mean that some sacrifices there were directed towards the Maize God. A head made of this material, interpreted as either depicting K\u2019inich Ajaw [kee-NEECH ah-\u201cHOW\u201d] or the Jester God, was found in a burial at Altun Ha. The Leiden Plate, on which one of the earliest known (*) Long Count dates are carved, is made of this material. The majority of this stone used by the Maya was mined from the region around the Motagua River. Pakal the Great was buried with a mask of this material, which was also a highly valued luxury in East Asia. For 10 points, what is this typically green semi-precious stone?", "answer": "William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke</u></b>", "acceptable": ["William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Bishop of Ferns apocryphally cursed this man to have no grandchildren through his sons for taking two of his estates, realized when all five of this man\u2019s sons died childless. During a siege of his father\u2019s castle during this man\u2019s childhood, a king threatened to launch this man at the castle via trebuchet, to which his father replied, \u201cI still have the hammer and the anvil with which to forge yet more and better sons!\u201d This man once unhorsed Richard the Lionheart in battle, but only demonstrated the fate he could have dealt Richard by killing his horse. At the age of 70, this man relieved the besieged forces of Nicola de la Haie at the (*) Second Battle of Lincoln. This man\u2019s prowess in tournament m\u00eal\u00e9e led to his appointment as military tutor to Young King Henry and his service to the crown through the reign of John. For 10 points, identify this foremost knight of late 12th century England.", "answer": "Sultanate of Malacca or Meleka  17. This movement vituperated a man who was converted to Catholicism by a priest best known for his poetry supporting this movement, Abram Joseph Ryan. Moses Jacob Ezekiel created a sculpture in support of this movement, which in raised letters references Cato from Lucan\u2019s Pharsalia. Educator Mildred Rutherford wrote the pamphlet \u201cA Measuring Rod\u201d, to advocate for school textbooks that aligned with this movement, which was endorsed by several former (*) generals. A \u201cCatechism\u201d for this movement used for teaching children argues for the importance of an attack on Fort Pickens. This movement led to the 1954 publication of the textbook History of Georgia, which claimed that barbecues and exposure to Christianity led to \u201ca close feeling of friendship between the slave and \u2018old massa.\u2019\u201d For 10 points, identify this movement after the Civil War to glorify the Confederacy and the antebellum South. ANSWER: \u201cLost\u201d Cause movement (prompt on \u201cConfederate revival\u201d, \u201cConfederate commemoration\u201d, \u201cThe South shall rise again\u201d, or other similar answers)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sultanate of Malacca or Meleka  17. This movement vituperated a man who was converted to Catholicism by a priest best known for his poetry supporting this movement, Abram Joseph Ryan. Moses Jacob Ezekiel created a sculpture in support of this movement, which in raised letters references Cato from Lucan\u2019s Pharsalia. Educator Mildred Rutherford wrote the pamphlet \u201cA Measuring Rod\u201d, to advocate for school textbooks that aligned with this movement, which was endorsed by several former</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Sultanate of Malacca or Meleka  17. This movement vituperated a man who was converted to Catholicism by a priest best known for his poetry supporting this movement, Abram Joseph Ryan. Moses Jacob Ezekiel created a sculpture in support of this movement, which in raised letters references Cato from Lucan\u2019s Pharsalia. Educator Mildred Rutherford wrote the pamphlet \u201cA Measuring Rod\u201d, to advocate for school textbooks that aligned with this movement, which was endorsed by several former"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "*"}, {"question": "In a story re-evaluated by socialist historian Kassim Ahmad, a ruler of this state brings a warrior out of hiding to defeat his friend who attacked the palace seeking justice. While serving this state, Tamils like the long-lived Tun Perak served in a post similar to a Prime Minister called a bendahara. After the fall of this state, isolated Tamils would form a community called the Chitty. The heavily romanticized story of a laksamana admiral serving this state\u2019s ruler Mansur Shah is told in the Hikayat Hang Tuah. According to the (*) Sulalatus Salatin, this state was founded by a man fleeing the collapse of a nearby island kingdom named Iskandar Shah, who is thought to be the same person as the more historically attested Parameswara. The sultanate of Johor was founded a decade after this state was conquered in 1511 by an expedition from Goa led by Afonso de Albuquerque. For 10 points, name this state in modern day Singapore and Malaysia that controlled trade in its namesake strait.", "answer": "Republic of Suriname", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Republic of Suriname</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Republic of Suriname"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This movement vituperated a man who was converted to Catholicism by a priest best known for his poetry supporting this movement, Abram Joseph Ryan. Moses Jacob Ezekiel created a sculpture in support of this movement, which in raised letters references Cato from Lucan\u2019s Pharsalia. Educator Mildred Rutherford wrote the pamphlet \u201cA Measuring Rod\u201d, to advocate for school textbooks that aligned with this movement, which was endorsed by several former (*) generals. A \u201cCatechism\u201d for this movement used for teaching children argues for the importance of an attack on Fort Pickens. This movement led to the 1954 publication of the textbook History of Georgia, which claimed that barbecues and exposure to Christianity led to \u201ca close feeling of friendship between the slave and \u2018old massa.\u2019\u201d For 10 points, identify this movement after the Civil War to glorify the Confederacy and the antebellum South.", "answer": "Prague (The uprising in the first line is the June (or Pentecostal) Uprising of 1848.)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Prague</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Prague"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "The uprising in the first line is the June (or Pentecostal"}, {"question": "Control of a colony in this country founded in 1683, called its \u201cSociety\u201d, was split three ways between its colonizer\u2019s capital, an East India Company, and the noble family that first governed it. A short-lived colony in this country was named after the governor of another colony, Lord Francis Willoughby, who introduced a fever that killed a third of its population on his second visit. Escaped slaves in this non-European country who mixed with native populations founded the six tribes of the (*) Bushinengue in its jungle interior. The end of slavery in this country in 1870 and the signing of the Recruitment Treaty with Great Britian led to the import of Indian labourers from British India, while Chinese and Javanese labourers were brought from its colonizer\u2019s Asian territories. In the Treaty of Westminster, Charles II traded lands in this country for New Amsterdam, which largely set the borders of this country with its English-speaking neighbour. For 10 points, identify this small country, the site of the major Dutch settlement of South America.", "answer": "Nile River", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Nile <b><u>River</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Nile River"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "During an uprising in this city, the wife of general Windischgr\u00e4tz was killed by a stray bullet, leading Windischgr\u00e4tz to bombard it mercilessly. A historian based in this city wrote \u201cIf the Austrian empire had not already existed...one would have to...in the interest of humanity, create it\u201d in his Reply to the Frankfurt Parliament. A professor and politician based in this city was married to the American Charlotte Garrigue and exposed a set of alleged Medieval poems, the \u201cGreen Mountain Manuscript\u201d, as a forgery. The first Slavic Congress was held in this city, which was where, after the National Police Force was purged of non-communist members, 12 cabinet ministers from parties such as the National Social party resigned. This site of Klement (*) Gottwald\u2019s \u201cVictorious February\u201d coup was also the site of an event during which the \u201cTwo Thousand Words\u201d manifesto was distributed and the Action Programme was pronounced. That event led to the creation of the Brezhnev doctrine and was followed by a period of \u201cNormalization\u201d.\u00a0 For 10 points, name this city, the home of Franti\u0161ek Palack\u00fd and Tomas Masayrk, the site of a 1968 \u201cspring\u201d.\u00a0", "category": "History"}, {"question": "After the Abbasid Revolution, the sons of Marwan II attempted to find refuge with King Kyriakos of a state on this river, but were refused. The inscription on a tombstone of a king named David found in the city of Soba is evidence of the influence of Greek as a liturgical language in states along this river. After an Arab army failed to take a city on this river, the defenders were titled \u201cpupil-smiters\u201d for the number of attackers their archers blinded. The construction of a dam on this river submerged the city of Faras, the capital of (*) Nobadia. A yearly tribute of slaves was sent north along this river as part of the Baqt treaty after the Second Battle of Dongola. It has been disputed as to whether an inscription on a stela in Ge\u2019ez in Mero\u00eb (\u201cmay-roe\u201d-ay), a city on this river, means that King Ezana of Aksum conquered the city. Medieval states developed after the decline of the Kingdom of Kush along, for 10 points, what river?", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}